Charity Adams Earley Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Charity Adams Earley Papers 1928-2002 (bulk 1942-2002)
MSS84973
Earley, Charity Adams, 1918-2002
1,000 items
8 containers plus 1 oversize
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
African-American army officer, educator, and civic activist. Book drafts, correspondence, military records, speeches, notes, press clippings, printed matter, and other papers relating to Earley’s experience as the first African-American commissioned officer in the Women’s Army Corps during World War II and her community activities later in life.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Earley, Charity Adams, 1918-2002.; Earley, Charity Adams, 1918-2002. One woman's Army: a Black officer remembers the WAC. 1989.
Organizations
United States. Army--African American troops.; United States. Army--Women.; United States. Army. Women's Army Corps.; United States. Army. Women's Army Corps. Central Postal Battalion, 6888th.
Subjects
African Americans--Segregation.; World War, 1939-1945--England--Birmingham.; World War, 1939-1945--France--Paris.; World War, 1939-1945--France--Rouen.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, African American.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, Female.
Places
Fort Des Moines (Iowa); United States--Armed Forces--African American officers.
Occupations
Army officers.; Civic activists.; Educators.
Provenance
The papers of Charity Adams Earley, African-American army officer, educator, and civic activist, were given to the Library of Congress by Stanley A. Earley, Jr., in 2003.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Charity Adams Earley Papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1918, Dec. 5 Born, Kittrell, N.C.
1938 B.A., Wilberforce University, Wilberforce, Ohio
1938 1942 Mathematics and science teacher, public school system, Columbia, S.C.
1942 1946 United States Army, Women’s Auxiliary Corps; served as company commander, staff training officer, and station control officer, Fort Des Moines, Iowa, (1942-1944) and commanding officer, 6888th Central Postal Directory Battalion, European Theater of Operations (1945)
1946 Retired from U. S. Army as lieutenant colonel M.A., Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio Registration officer, Veterans Administration, Cleveland, Ohio
1948 Dean of personnel services, Tennessee Agricultural and Industrial State College, Nashville, Tenn.
1948 1949 Dean of students, Georgia State College, Savannah, Ga.
1949 Married Stanley A. Earley, Jr.
1950 1952 Studied at University of Zurich and Jungian Institute of Analytical Psychology, Zurich, Switzerland
1965 1993 Board of directors, Dayton, Ohio, area chapter, American Red Cross
1972 1978 Board of governors, American Red Cross
1977 1992 Board of trustees, Sinclair Community College, Dayton, Ohio
1979 1991 Board of directors, Dayton Power and Light Co.
1982 Founder Black Leadership Development Program, Dayton, Ohio, 1989
1989 Published One Woman’s Army: A Black Officer Remembers the WAC. College Station: Texas A & M University Press Founding member, Parity 2000 (renamed Parity Inc.)
2002, Jan. 13 Died, Dayton, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Charity Edna Adams Earley (1918-2002) span the years 1928-2002, with the bulk of the material dating from 1942 to 2002. They are arranged into categories of general correspondence, speeches and writings, subject files, and oversize material. A large portion of the papers relates to Earley’s experiences during World War II as the first African-American commissioned officer in the Women’s Army Auxiliary Corps, which became the Woman’s Army Corps (WAC), and the highest ranking African-American woman to serve overseas during the war.
Earley’s memoir, One Woman’s Army: A Black Officer Remembers the WAC, recounts her experiences as a woman and as an African American in the segregated military at Fort Des Moines, Iowa, and as commanding officer of the 6888th Central Postal Battalion stationed in Birmingham, England, and Rouen and Paris, France. Additional information on her activities during World War II are contained in military records, press clippings, and speeches.
Included in the subject files are materials relating to organizations and programs which Charity Adams Earley served as a board member and events at which she was honored for her accomplishments.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material or topic.
Container List
- General correspondence, 1942-1944, 1986-2002, undated See also Oversize, (10 folders) (Box 1)
- Speeches and writings (Box 1)
  - Book, One Woman’s Army: A Black Officer Remembers the WAC (Box 1)
    - Drafts (Box 1)
      - Draft 1, 1946, (2 folders) (Box 1)
      - Draft 2, pre-1986, (5 folders) (Box 2)
      - Draft 3, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 2)
      - Draft 4, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 2)
      - Draft 5, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - Draft 6, 1986, (3 folders) (Box 3)
      - Draft 7, 1987, (1 folder); (2 folders) (Box 3, Box 4)
      - Draft 8, 1987, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - Draft 9, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
      - Miscellany, 1942-1948, 1987, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Miscellany, 1989-1997, undated (Box 5)
    - Texas A & M University Press, 1994-2002, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 1995, undated (Box 5)
  - Speaking engagements, 1979, 1990-1997, (2 folders) (Box 5)
- Subject file (Box 5)
  - American Red Cross, 1972, 1981, 1993-2001 (Box 5)
  - Dayton Urban League, Black Leadership Development Program, Dayton, Ohio, 1986-1999, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - DPL Inc., 1987-1990 (Box 6)
  - “Glory and Destiny,” salute to African Americans who served in World War II, Washington, D.C., 1995 (Box 6)
  - Honors and awards, 1965-1967, 1979-1982, 1990-2002, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Military records, 1942-1945, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, 1928-1934, 1990-2002, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - National Association of Black Military Women, 1989-1999, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - National World War II Memorial, Washington, D.C., 2000-2001 (Box 7)
  - Parity Inc., 1989-2002, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Printed matter (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974, 1984-2002, undated, (5 folders) (Box 7)
    - Press clippings, 1942-1948, 1965-1967, 1981-1983, 1989-2002, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Women in Military Service for America Memorial, Washington, D.C., 1994-2001, undated See also Oversize, (5 folders) (Box 8)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - General correspondence, 1996, (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
  - Subject file (Box OV 1)
    - Women in Military Service for America Memorial, Washington, D.C., 2000, (Container 8) (Box OV 1)